Okay בוקר טוב Boker tov everybody. Today's דף daf is ס"ו, Samech
Vav, sixty-six, and as we're about to see and as we saw
yesterday, we're now in the middle of the part of this מסכת
masechet that is learned when people are learning כשרות kashrus and you
know issues about ביטול bittul and mixtures and so on. And yesterday
we introduced the whole idea
of, well the משנה Mishnah mentioned the whole idea of נותן טעם,
nosein taam, that something is only problematic if it gives a taste,
and even then only if it's נותן טעם לפגם, nosein taam lifgam,
if it's a bad taste, it's not an issue. Along the way,
the גמרא Gemara first dealt with a sort of side concern that
when something got mixed up in the wine on the grain or
whatever, if you don't, if you can't eat the grain, how can
you sell to a non-Jew, you're afraid he might turn around and
go ahead and sell it to a Jew? Okay, so anyway, so
now the גמרא Gemara though continues. And
but of course the thing has to absorb, so the question is
how does the wine get absorbed? So the משנה Mishnah speaks about
if like you're dealing with something like you know figs or dates
or whatever where the skin is porous. But if you're dealing with
grapes, then the stuff doesn't get exactly, doesn't wouldn't get absorbed and
you just rinse off the surface. Although תוספות Tosafos pointed out, which
I didn't mention yesterday, that it's talking about that the grapes are
still connected to the vine, not the vine but whatever they're on
the cluster, they're on the twig you know when you have it
like from the supermarket, you haven't plucked them. But if you pluck
them off of their little twig, then you expose, the hole exposes
it, so it would get absorbed there. So that's an issue about
absorption even when stuff is cold. If you're dealing with liquids and
porous stuff, you obviously don't need heat to transfer taste in those
types of cases. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara picks up on
the top of ס"ו עמוד א Samech Vav amud aleph because the
principle as I mentioned to you and one might say it's what's
going on in the משנה Mishnah as well, but we'll see in
a minute about that. The principle about יין נסך yayin nesech is
that we have an extra stringency like we do by
חמץ בפסח, chametz b'Pesach, that it's בטל battel even במשהו, bemashehu, even
a tiniest amount. However, by יין נסך yayin nesech and that's only
when it's מין במינו, min bemino, it's all the same type of
thing. Because I should just sort of mention this,
why is it? Is when something gets mixed up like and like,
is that a bigger problem or less of a problem? So there's
actually a debate in הלכה halacha about that. ר' יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says that when something is mixed up like and like, even if
it's not... listen. If something gets mixed up like and like in
general, let's say it's not יין נסך, yayin nesech, let's say you
have I don't know a little bit of soup from meat that
was not שחט shechted properly, נבילה, neveilah, mixing up
in soup of meat that was שחט shechted properly. So you could
say what we actually פסק pasken is that in principle that's בטל
battel even ברוב, berov, as long as there's like fifty-one percent of
kosher stew. Because in practice we say you need sixty times as
much because you know we want to be sort of as a
safeguard, an extension of the idea of when it's מין באינו מינו.
min be'eino mino. But anyway, but in principle that really should be
בטל battel even ברוב. berov. Because since the non-kosher beef stew doesn't
give off any taste, so if there's no taste, it's like it's
not present and then you should exactly the same thing. Michael, let
me finish. Okay, it's like it's not present... מין במינו, min bemino,
same taste, okay. So since it gives off the same taste, since
it doesn't give off any special taste, it doesn't make its presence
felt that way and therefore we'll define the entity by the majority,
you know, majority rules. All right, so as long as there's fifty-one
percent, you know, it should all be considered kosher stew. However, if
it's אינו מינו, eino mino, a drop of blood let's say falls
into your beef stew, then it can make its presence felt through
being tasted. That's the principle of the משנה Mishnah about נותן טעם.
nosein taam. Okay, so that's the general assumption that when something is
with the case of מין באינו מינו, min be'eino mino, it's a
bigger problem because its presence can be felt and it's not enough
that there's a majority, you need there to be actually
like you know a large proportion has to be the kosher. The
טריפה treif can only be like the general rule of course we
go by is one-sixtieth, less than one-sixtieth, and in that way its
taste cannot be felt. That's the non-kosher, that's אינו מינו. eino mino.
But by מינו mino maybe in principle, rabbinically not, but in principle
even a majority. However,
ר' יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is of the position that we always say
מין במינו min bemino is never בטל. battel. Why? Because he makes
the opposite argument. He says, okay, I get that in the case
of the beef stew mixed up with the kosher beef stew and
the non-kosher beef stew, that the non-kosher doesn't make its presence felt
because you can't taste it. But on the other hand, its presence
is always felt because every spoon you taste has the taste of
meat and you're also tasting the non-kosher food. So because it's basically
it's all the same, it doesn't lose its identity. It doesn't make
its identity felt, but it also because there's no difference, doesn't have
its identity erased either. Anyways, that's the general principle. So, when you
come to certain areas of הלכה halacha like יין נסך Yayin Nesech
where we want to be strict and we want to say that
it's not בטל batel even במשהו, be-mashehu, we rather than say we
only למעשה le-ma'aseh we say that only by מין במינו, min be-mino,
not by מין באינו מינו. min be-eino mino. Why? I mean, you
know, if יין נסך Yayin Nesech is very weighty, then we should
be weighty across the board. What, is it more weighty when wine
gets mixed up with wine than when wine falls into my soup?
So the answer is no, it's not that it's more weighty in
that case, but often what the Rabbis want is they want even
when they want to be strict, they want to build it on
a pre-existing halachic model. So essentially what they choose to do is
they say we want to be strict by יין נסך Yayin Nesech
and we want to say it's only it's not בטל batel even
במשהו. be-mashehu. What we'll do is we'll employ רבי יהודה'ס Rabbi Yehuda's
reasoning. We normally don't rule like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. We normally
rule מין במינו min be-mino is בטל batel even ברוב. be-rov. But
if we want to be strict by רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in
יין נסך, Yayin Nesech, we're going to rule like רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda is essentially what the Rabbis are saying. So in יין נסך,
Yayin Nesech, if wine gets mixed up with wine, it's אסור assur
even במשהו. be-mashehu. Okay, but if wine falls into your soup, then
we go by the normal principle of נותן טעם. nosen ta'am. So
that's the general idea that we should know going forward, that by
יין נסך, Yayin Nesech, now there's an interesting question what do you
say about סתם יינם, stam yeinam, okay, but we're just now going
to assume יין נסך. Yayin Nesech. By יין נסך Yayin Nesech מין
במינו min be-mino is במשהו, be-mashehu, it's never בטל, batel, wine and
wine, okay, but wine in anything else when it's אינו מינו, eino
mino, it goes by the normal principles of נותן טעם nosen ta'am
of only if it's able to be tasted. Yes, Mike. I was
trying to get at before was like, you know, your case was
exactly the same, but like let's say it's I don't know let's
take an easy example, let's say coffee ice cream and vanilla ice
cream. They're very different. You know what I mean? Is that how
how how is that? So that's essentially what the גמרא Gemara is
going to get to. So let's look at the very first line
now of the גמרא Gemara in ס"ו. Samech-Vav. How do you define
מינו mino and אינו מינו eino mino since this really matters by
the issue of wine since once it's defined as מינו mino the
הלכה halacha is it's אסור במשהו. assur be-mashehu. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, top of ס"ו עמוד א': Samech-Vav Amud Aleph: חמרא
עתיקא באינבי. Chamra atika be-invi. So you have old wine that gets
mixed up, that gets absorbed into grapes, okay? דברי הכל בנותן טעם.
Divrei hakol be-nosen ta'am. That goes by taste because it is both
called something different, wine and grapes, and it tastes different. Old wine
tastes different than grapes. חמרא חדתא באינבי, Chamra chadata be-invi, new wine,
which essentially is like grape juice, unfermented wine, באינבי be-invi gets absorbed
into grapes. So do you define that as מינו mino or
אינו מינו? eino mino? אביי אמר במשהו. Abaye amar be-mashehu. That's אסור
במשהו, assur be-mashehu, that's considered like and like and it's אסור במשהו.
assur be-mashehu. ורבא אמר בנותן טעם. ve-Rava amar be-nosen ta'am. It goes
by taste and therefore why? Because it's considered like and unlike. And
therefore so אביי אמר במשהו בתר טעמא אזלינן. Abaye amar be-mashehu batar
ta'ama azlinan. So אביי Abaye says, look, the issue of is something
the same or not boils down to does it taste the same
or not, okay, especially based on the principle that I started with,
right, like can it be felt because is its presence felt because
of its taste? So anyway here where the tastes are the same,
how is this the same exactly? במשהו? be-mashehu? Grape juice, new wine
is grape juice, okay? So grape juice getting mixed up, getting absorbed
in grapes, it all tastes the same. All right? Okay. If you
so so if you take natural grape juice, right, you know, not
the stuff... Without sugar? Without the sugar and you basically you soak
your grapes in them, they they might taste extra juicy but they're
not there's not going to be a distinct taste. Okay? So אביי
Abaye says that since it all tastes the same, we consider it
to be like and like מין במינו min be-mino and therefore the
principle is במשהו. be-mashehu. Okay? Its presence isn't distinct, but that's what
I said the flip. On the one hand, its presence isn't felt
because it doesn't have a distinct taste, but it also its presence
isn't there's no difference so that its presence is lost. It all
it all is there. It all tastes like you know you're tasting
the grape juice as you're biting into the grapes. So it's all
there. So anyway because here we use the מין במינו במשהו min
be-mino be-mashehu principle and this is considered מינו. mino. That's what אביי
Abaye says. בתר טעמא אזלינן. Batar ta'ama azlinan. You go by taste
since it tastes the same, it's מינו. mino. האי ואידי חד טעמא
הוא. Hai ve-idach chad ta'ama hu. It all tastes the same. דהוי
ליה מין במינו. De-havei lei min be-mino. ומין במינו במשהו. u-min be-mino
be-mashehu. Here here at least מין במינו min be-mino is במשהו. be-mashehu.
I'll discuss in general in a minute but here certainly by wine
we rule that מין במינו min be-mino is במשהו. be-mashehu. ורבא אמר
בנותן טעם. ve-Rava amar be-nosen ta'am. No.
It loses its identity by measured by what it gives taste. Now
of course it's a little ironic since it all tastes the same,
it never gives taste, but נותן טעם nosen ta'am means either you
check to see if it's tasteable or if you can't check like
here because it all tastes the same, you go by one and
sixty. So רבא Rava says it would be בטל batel if it
would be less than 1/60th. בתר שמא אזלינן. Batar shma azlinan. You
go by what it's named. Okay? והאי שמא לחוד והאי שמא לחוד.
Ve-hai shma le-chud ve-hai shma le-chud. And grapes and wine have a
different name. So therefore it's considered like with
unlike מין באינו מינו. min be-eino mino. And the principle is... it
goes by one in sixty. Okay, now, one minute. Okay, now והוה
ליה מין בשאינו מינו, v'havei lei min b'sheino mino, it's like with
unlike,
ומין בשאינו מינו בנותן טעם, umin b'sheino mino b'noten ta'am, and you
go by taste. Okay, so רבא Rava says you go by the
name, it's, it gets a little confusing. You go by the name
and since you go by the name you go by taste. But
in this case, meaning, the it's מינו mino is defined and אינו
מינו eino mino is defined by name. Since these things have a
different name, by the way, which is pretty funny, you know, because
that's really like just a human artifact, it's not something objectively true
about the object, it's more sort of like socially how we categorize
things. On the other hand, you know, okay, I mean, הלכה halakha
sort of does deal with real human realities, and how we name
things does is an exact reflection of how as a society, what
category we put things in. So if you want to say is
it the same category or different category, if we use different names,
we're saying that we we've defined things, we define it, you know,
in terms of categories as in a different category. So רבא Rava
says because we use different names it's a different category and therefore
here as מין בשאינו מינו min b'sheino mino you would go by
one and sixty.
We're about eight lines down on ס"ו
עמוד א'. Samech Vav Amud Aleph. Okay, בנותן טעם. b'noten ta'am. Now,
תנן. Tnan. Now we're going to try to prove, you know, אביי
Abaye or רבא's Rava position from the משנה. Mishna. יין נסך שנפל
על גבי ענבים. Yayin nesekh shenafal agabei anavim. It spoke about if
wine fell on grapes and it said that if the grapes were
cracked it's forbidden. Now, if you ask me the simple meaning of
that follows אביי, Abaye, seems to say that it goes that since
it doesn't say in the beginning of the משנה Mishna that you
go by taste it just says straight away that the grapes are
forbidden if the grapes were cracked, it seems to be saying that
we consider that to be מין במינו. min b'mino. Okay, let's see
so which would be like אביי, Abaye, but let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says.
קסלקא דעתך חמרא חדתא בענבי. Kasalka deitakh khamra khadata b'invei. We assumed
we were talking about new wine.
מאי לאו בנותן טעם? Mai lav b'noten ta'am? So rather than the
fact that the משנה Mishna just straight says they're forbidden, the גמרא
Gemara says doesn't the משנה Mishna mean they're forbidden if they give
taste since that's the discussion at the end of the משנה Mishna
about taste? So presumably when it said forbidden at the beginning it
meant forbidden if it gave taste. So מאי לאו בנותן טעם? mai
lav b'noten ta'am? לא, במשהו. Lo, b'mashehu. No, the beginning of the
משנה Mishna means that it's אסור assur even a small amount which
would be an exact proof to אביי, Abaye, grape juice absorbed in
wine is considered מין במינו min b'mino it's even a little amount.
One minute, הא מכדי תני סיפא ha mikhtani seifa since the end
of the משנה Mishna when it discusses the parameters says זה הכלל,
Zeh Haklal, uses a line, doesn't just give a case of בנותן
טעם, b'noten ta'am, uses a line that says the rule is
בנותן טעם. b'noten ta'am. כל שנתן בנותן טעם אסור, כל שלא נתן
בנותן טעם מותר. Kol shebanatan b'noten ta'am assur, kol shelo banatan b'noten
ta'am mutar. That if it gives good taste it's forbidden.
מכלל דבנותן טעם עסקינן. Mikhlal de'bnoten ta'am askinan. So it seems like
that rule applies even to the beginning of the משנה, Mishna, which
I hear. It's a little bit funny. The beginning of the משנה
Mishna one hand just says straight away forbidden, doesn't say it has
to if it gives taste, to me would be indicate a משהו.
mashehu. But the משנה Mishna never gives a never says זה הכלל
מין במינו במשהו. Zeh Haklal min b'mino b'mashehu. It never says that.
The only principle in the משנה Mishna is בנותן טעם. b'noten ta'am.
So it says presumably that's the principle at the beginning of the
משנה Mishna as well. So why is it בנותן טעם b'noten ta'am
according to אביי? Abaye? Since it since it's מין במינו, min b'mino,
grape juice and grapes, it should all be במשהו. b'mashehu. ואביי, Va'Abaye,
so אביי Abaye has an easy answer, מתניתין בחמרא עתיקא בענבי. matnitin
b'khamra attika b'invei.
Our משנה Mishna is talking about old wine. Since it's old wine,
it's different because the standard would be old wine. The standard would
be fermented wine which is a different taste than grapes. So the
משנה Mishna doesn't have to bother me says אביי, Abaye, even if
I agree with you that the beginning of the משנה Mishna means
בנותן טעם, b'noten ta'am, we're talking about old wine, we're talking about
a different taste than grapes. But אביי Abaye would still say that
if it tastes the same, it's considered מין במינו. min b'mino. Now,
אביי Abaye is not the which position you take it's not a
clear חומרא humra or קולא kula position because one case it could
be a חומרא humra and one case it could be a קולא.
kula. In the case we just dealt with, you know, grape juice
and grapes, אביי Abaye saying you go by taste would be a
חומרא, humra, that would be משהו. mashehu. רבא Rava would be a
קולא, kula, he'd say that's מין ושאינו מינו min v'sheino mino and
it's one and sixty. But sometimes it could reverse itself. So let's
look at the next case of the גמרא. Gemara.
חלא דחמרא וחלא דשיכרא. Khala d'khamra v'khala d'shikhra. Let's say you have
and this is like Michael here's where you can plug in your
ice cream example. You have wine vinegar and beer vinegar, okay? So
they're both called vinegar but they both have very distinct taste. You
have vanilla ice cream and chocolate ice cream. Okay, or חמירא khamira
not חמרא, khamra, חמירא דחיטי וחמירא דשערי. khamira d'khitei v'khamira d'se'arei. What
does חמירא khamira mean? Anybody? We're getting coming up to פסח. Pesakh.
כל חמיא וחמירא דאיכא ברשותי. Kol khamia v'khamira d'ika birshuti. Right, yeast
of like dough, sourdough of wheat and of barley. חמרא Khamra comes
from the same root. What? חמרא Khamra is from the is the
Aramaic... Oh, that's interesting. חמרא Khamra for wine is because of fermenting.
Oh, I hadn't put those... חמירא Khamira from the same... Nice, nice.
Okay, so fermenting, meaning yeast, sourdough, of wheat and of barley. Okay,
so here are things that are called the same but have very
different tastes. So is it מין במינו min b'mino or אינו מינו?
eino mino? So אביי אמר בנותן טעם. Abaye amar b'noten ta'am. אביי
Abaye says those are considered to be like and and unlike and
therefore it goes by the rule of one and sixty or... Is
it can you taste it when you mix it together? אביי Abaye
makes the most sense if you ask me. Anyway, בתר טעמא אזלינן,
batar ta'ama azlinan, והאי טעמא לחוד ve-hai ta'ama lachud והאי טעמא לחוד,
ve-hai ta'ama lachud, those are distinct tastes, והוי ליה מין בשאינו מינו,
ve-havei lei min be-she-eino mino, and it's like with unlike, ומין בשאינו
מינו בנותן טעם, u-min be-she-eino mino be-nosein ta'am, and that goes with
its ability to be tasted and therefore if it's less than one
and sixty or maybe you don't even need one and sixty if
you just have a non-Jew taste it or whatever the case might
be. If you go ahead and taste it and it's not tastable,
therefore it's בטל. batel. You go by taste. Stay one minute. ורבא
אמר במין במינו, u-Rava amar be-min be-mino, רבא Rava says no, you
these are considered to be all the same, מין במינו, min be-mino,
and even if it can't be tasted it's forbidden because and it
is forbidden even in a small amount. בתר שמא אזלינן, batar shema
azlinan, you go by what they're called, והאי חלא מקרי ve-hai chala
mikrei והאי חלא מקרי, ve-hai chala mikrei, they're both called vinegar in
the first case. והאי חמירא מקרי ve-hai chamira mikrei והאי חמירא מקרי,
ve-hai chamira mikrei, or they're both called sourdough in the second case,
והוי ליה מין במינו, ve-havei lei min be-mino, and it's like and
like, וכל מין במינו במשהו, ve-chol min be-mino be-mashehu, it always goes
with a משהו. mashehu. Now I want to just pause a second
because I have told you at the beginning that the general rule
is that מין במינו min be-mino is בטל ברוב, batel be-rov, but
by יין, Yayin, יין נסך yayin nesech where we want to be
strict we go to the opposite extreme and we adopt רבי יהודה's
Rabbi Yehuda's model and we say that it's במשהו. be-mashehu. Here however
the case of vinegar could be a יין נסך yayin nesech example.
Vinegar's included in יין נסך. yayin nesech. Okay, but the problem about
wheat sourdough, that's not a יין נסך yayin nesech example. Maybe it's
a חמץ בפסח chametz be-Pesach example. There also you go by משהו,
mashehu, but normally we assume חמץ בפסח chametz be-Pesach is משהו. mashehu.
We're so strict by חמץ בפסח chametz be-Pesach that we say that
it's במשהו be-mashehu even by אינו מינו, eino mino, right? I mean
I know people know that, right? That the problem by פסח Pesach
why you have to buy all those כשר לפסח kosher le-Pesach stuff
and so on is because even in אינו מינו eino mino it's
משהו. mashehu. So what's the example of these different types of sourdoughs
getting mixed up? So if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi
says three lines from the top, the last word of the line,
חמירא דחטי וחמירא דשערי, chamira de-chiti ve-chamira de-sa'ari, רש"י Rashi says חד
דחולין וחד דתרומה. chad de-chullin ve-chad de-terumah. The case would be we're
dealing with תרומה. terumah. Okay, we're dealing with תרומה terumah but why
are we going by משהו? mashehu? We should go by ששים, shishim,
sometimes by תרומה terumah you go by one in a hundred, but
why are we going by משהו? mashehu?
So רש"י Rashi says וכל מין במינו במשהו, ve-chol min be-mino be-mashehu,
רש"י Rashi says לקמן פסקינן דלאו הלכתא הכי le-kaman paskinan de-lav hilchata
hachi אלא אפילו מין במינו בנותן טעם ella afilu min be-mino be-nosein
ta'am חוץ מטבל ויין נסך. chutz mi-tevel ve-yayin nesech. So רש"י Rashi
says actually this גמרא Gemara is assuming רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. This
גמרא, Gemara, the line in the גמרא Gemara if you picked it
up was רבא Rava when it says ומין במינו וכל מין במינו
במשהו, u-min be-mino ve-chol min be-mino be-mashehu, not מין במינו min be-mino
by יין נסך, yayin nesech, כל מין במינו kol min be-mino is
משהו. mashehu. So this גמרא Gemara because it's introducing the case about
the wheat, about the the dough, and because of that line כל
מין במינו kol min be-mino is actually assuming we always rule like
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in all cases. So if you got a
little טרפה, treifa, you know, whatever meat mixed up with kosher meat
or whatever little טרף treif beef stew, it would be you wouldn't
say, oh, it's בטל, batel, it's ששים. shishim. You would say, מין
במינו min be-mino everything it's במשהו. be-mashehu. Now you should know that
רש"י Rashi in a number of places in ש"ס, Shas, חולין Chullin
in particular, paskens like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and says that like
in all areas of כשרות, kashrus, מין במינו min be-mino would be
במשהו. be-mashehu. Good thing we don't, you know, תוספות Tosafot would be
a problem. It would always be a problem. So תוספות Tosafot and
whatever, you know, roundly rejects רש"י Rashi and it's a good thing.
I mean imagine how much more difficult כשרות kashrus would be if
whenever there was a case of, oh, it's like and like, we
would always have to say that it's במשהו. be-mashehu. Here רש"י Rashi
also rejects it. So רש"י Rashi's a little inconsistent. If you notice
there's a note on your side that says רש"י Rashi's inconsistent with
what he says elsewhere. רש"י Rashi here says this גמרא Gemara says
מין במינו min be-mino is במשהו be-mashehu but the הלכה halacha is
not that way. The הלכה halacha מין במינו min be-mino is במשהו
be-mashehu is pretty much limited to wine and טבל tevel and חמץ,
chametz, but by חמץ chametz it's always במשהו. be-mashehu. So that's what
תוספות Tosafot would say. Yeah and yeah and רש"י Rashi here says
but not רש"י Rashi elsewhere. Okay. So anyway so for your purposes
you have to know that the emphasis of the idea of מין
במינו במשהו min be-mino be-mashehu is what's going to be when talking
about our עבודה זרה avodah zarah concerns about יין נסך. yayin nesech.
Okay. And then there's an interesting question about סתם יינם. stam yeinam.
Okay. But anyway but the גמרא Gemara here does bring in a
case of wheat and dough and so on, but for our purposes
the focus is by if you want to know in terms of
למעשה le-ma'aseh הלכה, halacha, practical הלכה, halacha, the משהו mashehu issue basically
comes up and the difference between משהו mashehu by מין במינו min
be-mino versus אינו מינו eino mino that when it's מינו mino it's
משהו mashehu is basically a יין נסך yayin nesech issue. It doesn't
really apply in pretty much other areas. But not סתם יינם? stam
yeinam? Well I'll get to סתם יינם stam yeinam later. Okay. So
now let's continue going. Okay.
אמר אמר אביי מנא אמינא לה. amar amar Abaye mena amina lah.
אביי Abaye says, okay, where do I get my idea that to
define like and unlike we go by how it tastes? דבתר טעמא
אזלינן, de-batar ta'ama azlinan, you go by taste. דתניא de-tanya we turn
a ברייתא. Braitah. תבלין
ב' וג' שמות הן, tavlin bet ve-gimmel shemot hen, if you have
spices, I'm going to read this the way תוספות Tosafot reads this,
if you have spices of different types of איסורים. issurim. Like you've
got some pepper that's ערלה orlah and some pepper that's טבל tevel
and some pepper I don't know that somebody bowed down to, and
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Okay, anyway whatever it is, you have different
types. So שמות shemot here רש"י Rashi says it means different names
like we've been talking about before, like what you call them. But
תוספות Tosafot says no, שמות shemot yeah yeah whatever, שמות shemot in
this context means תוספות Tosafot says, you know, the nature of the
איסור. issur. So you have them, okay, והן מין אחד, vehen min
echad, they're all pepper. They're all the same peppers but they're a
mix of ערלה orlah and טבל tevel and whatever. Okay, and then
they all get mixed up into a stew. Okay, או מין ג'
o min gimmel or they're three different types of spices, pepper and
cinnamon and whatnot, okay, and, you know, and the what's missing here
is and they're all one איסור. issur. You have pepper and spices
and I don't know and and and cinnamon and nutmeg and they're
all ערלה, orlah, okay, and they all get mixed up.
אסורין ומצטרפין, assurin umitzstarfin, they combine and they make things forbidden. Now,
תוספות Tosafot says the double language of combine, isn't that the same
point? Like one is talking about לח בלח, lach belach, the other
יבש ביבש, yavesh beyavesh, but anyway the point is they combine. Now
the question is, why do they combine? Okay? If they are really
different things, if you've got pepper and cinnamon and nutmeg, how do
they all combine to, you know, to make something forbidden? So they're,
you know, they're different things, different things shouldn't combine. So אביי Abbaye
says aha, this is my proof, because they have well wait one
minute. Does that work? Or is that no, is that already רבא?
Rava? Oh, because the next line is חזקיה, Chizkiyah, excuse me. ואמר
חזקיה Ve'amar Chizkiyah and חזקיה Chizkiyah said, I forgot that line. Okay,
הכא במיני מתיקה עסקינן, hacha bemeine mitika askinan, הוברין למתק את הקדירה.
hovrin lematik et hakedeirah.
The that they combine because they are all they all give a
certain sweetness. So it would be an example, so the pepper example
might not be good. It might have to be like sugar and
corn syrup and what's that other thing people use as a sweetener?
Stevia? No, not that's a fake one, but there's other things like
date sugar, date honey or something. Whatever it is. Anyway, they're all
different but they all give a similar type of a sweetness. Okay?
So אביי Abbaye says ah, that's the only reason that they combine
is because they all ultimately function together to give a type of
a sweetness. So you see that you go by טעם. ta'am. הוברין
למתק את הקדירה. hovrin lematik et hakedeirah. אי אמרת בשלמא בתר טעמא
אזלינן, ei amart bishlama batar ta'ama azlinan, כולי חד טעמא הוא. kulei
chad ta'ama hu. So now it all makes sense. Because they all
have give this sweetness, they're all considered one thing and they combine
to make it forbidden. Meaning if you now if each one by
itself would not be enough to make the stuff forbidden, this is
actually a little bit ironic because we're talking here about an אינו
מינו eino mino case. You know the אביי Abbaye רבא Rava debate
is about a מינו. mino. How do you define מינו mino to
say במשהו? bemashehu? But this is a case but but if it
was a במשהו bemashehu you wouldn't need them to combine. The case
here is an אינו מינו eino mino case. You don't have enough
of any one of them to make the mixture forbidden, but when
you combine all three there's enough it gives off taste it makes
it forbidden and so on. So it's a little funny what exactly
the proof is. But his proof is yeah, they're giving the same
taste. But his proof is you wouldn't even think of combining things
that are fundamentally of different categories.
The fact that you're able to whatever just the fact that you're
able to combine them shows that because they have the same taste
we're able to think of them as one type of a thing.
So the table of chemistry like dissolves them. Right. You can get
sweet and sour fish, you know what I mean? I understand, I
understand. Okay. But that no, it rests on חזקיה's Chizkiyah's point about
that they're all מיני מתיקה. meinei matika. So he says you see,
even though they're different types of things, okay, and maybe even different
איסורים issurim or whatever they might be, we're able to combine them
because they have a similar taste. So you see that similar taste
is something that creates a sense of identity. אלא אי אמרת בתר
שמא אזלינן, ela ei amart batar shma azlinan, האי שמא לחוד והאי
שמא לחוד. hai shma lechud vehai shma lechud. In the case that
one of them was like, you know, what do you call it?
One of them was was ערלה orlah and one was טבל tevel
and one was something else, so why should the fact that they're
all types of sweetener allow you to conceptually combine them? They're all
if according to you רבא, Rava, that you think about things like
identity based on their names and taste is not part of their
identity. So it's true now there's a sweetness in the mixture, but
why is it that there's an איסור issur here that's אוסר-ing osser
the mixture? There's not, you know, because these three things are completely
distinct. They're all different identities and therefore what allows them to combine
to say that the mixture is forbidden? So ורבא אמר לך, veRava
amar lecha, so רבא Rava would say to you, הא מני רבי
מאיר היא. ha manni Rabbi Meir hi. This is רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. דתניא רבי יהודה אומר משום רבי מאיר, detanya Rabbi Yehuda omer
mishum Rabbi Meir, מנין לכל איסורין שבתורה שמצטרפין זה עם זה. minayin
lechol issurin shebatorah shemitztarfin zeh im zeh. No, there is some generic
identity even in terms of their name, again name meaning here their
איסור issur name, that allows them to combine. Why? What do you
mean? One is ערלה orlah and one is כלאים kilayim and one
is I don't know עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So he says no,
שנאמר, shene'emar, לא תאכל כל תועבה, lo tochal kol to'evah, don't eat
anything that's an abomination. כל שתיעבתי לך הרי הוא בבל תאכל. kol
sheti'avti lecha harei hu beval tochal. Anything that is forbidden shares a
generic identity. You know, we would sort of call it טרף. treif.
That's its generic name. identity, okay? So since all the, and they're
all part of this לאו Lav of לא תאכל כל תועבה. Lo
Tochal Kol Toeva. So says רבא, Rava, you asked said to me,
how do you know, like you said look, one is טבל, Tevel,
one is ערלה, Orla, and one is כלאים. Kilayim. And the fact
that we're able to combine them and say, oh, there's a problem
in this sweet stuff in this mixture because we have something problematic
that's sweet, and you אביי Abaye said, but it's not one thing
that's problematic. If you were to go by names as creating identities,
there's not one thing that's problematic. So says רבא, Rava, there is
one thing that's problematic because it's טריפה, Treifa, it's טריפה. Treif. So
that is an identity too. They all share this identity of טריפות
Treifus and that allows them therefore to combine to create this type
of a problem. Okay, so that's how, so therefore you can't really
prove it from there. It's not just their shared identity of tasting
sweet, it's their shared identity of being טריפה. Treif. All right, so
now the גמרא Gemara continues. Therefore you need enough to be נותן
טעם Nosein Taam according to רבא? Rava? Well and you need enough
to be, well, now the funny thing is that you also do
need them all to be sweet because otherwise each identity would be
lost, right? So that's why, I mean, תוספות Tosafos sort of figures
it out. Like according to אביי, Abaye, you know why you need
them to be sweet, because that's what allows them to combine and
to be seen as the same. But according to רבא, Rava, why
do you need them to be sweet? So רבא Rava would say
to you, look, if they weren't in a mixture, if you had
like a third of a כזית Kezayis of נבילה, Neveila, a third
of a כזית Kezayis of ערלה, Orla, a third of a כזית
Kezayis of כלאים, Kilayim, and a third of a כזית Kezayis of
טבל, Tevel, you know, and then you ate them, fine. You wouldn't
need them all to taste sweet. That would be transgressing לא תאכל
כל תועבה. Lo Tochal Kol Toeva. But in this case, the reason,
so fundamentally,
they combine because of their shared identity of תועבה. Toeva. That allows
you to see it as a unit. But in the case where
they get mixed up with something else, you need them also to
share a taste or otherwise, you know, they would just be בטל
Batel because they wouldn't have their, their presence wouldn't be felt. But
אביי Abaye says their whole shared identity is their shared taste. So
אביי Abaye sort of, that's what אביי Abaye emphasizes. Their whole shared
identity, all identity is created through distinct or different tastes, so their
whole shared identity comes from shared taste. And רבא Rava says no,
you need shared taste so that they're still present in the mixture,
but their shared identity comes from the fact that they're all תועבה,
Toeva, comes from their name. Okay? Is that pretty clear to people?
Yes, no, sort of? Okay, fine. And for אביי Abaye though, but
again,
it'd have to be נותן טעם, Nosein Taam, right? Because like you
still have to have, it has to have an impact. Yeah, yeah,
yeah. So if you had a third of a כזית Kezayis of
ערלה Orla and a third of a כזית Kezayis of whatever טבל,
Tevel, and a third of a כזית Kezayis of כלאים, Kilayim, okay,
and these were, you know, so אביי Abaye would basically say, oh,
these are all called different things and therefore they're, and therefore if
you ate all three of them, you would be פטור Patur because
you didn't eat one אסור Assur thing. And, and, and, excuse me,
I misstated it. Okay, but they're all sweet, they're all מתוק. Matok.
Or we're not assuming that they're all the same spice, just אסור
Assur for different reasons? Yeah, so we're assuming that they are,
we're assuming that they are,
yeah, that's, it sounds like we're assuming that they're different spices, they're
different types, sort of the example I gave, like sugar and, you
know, date honey and whatever. So they have, but they're sort of,
but they do have this, so, so they're different identities, their names
are different, right? They're different איסורים, Issurim, this is sugar and this
is honey and this is I don't know date honey or something
like that, okay? So their names, their names are all different, their
names are all different, and their איסור Issur are all different. So
אביי Abaye says so what allows us to combine it, right? So
אביי Abaye says well what allows us to combine it is that
they all taste the same. Okay, so these are the names and
these are the tastes, okay? So אביי Abaye says what allows us
to combine it is that they all taste the same, and that's
my proof that you go by taste. And רבא Rava says no,
what allows us to combine it is that they're all based on
this other פסוק, Pasuk, they're all תועבה, Toeva, they all have that
shared identity, and that shared identity of תועבה Toeva is what allows
us to combine it, okay? So even though they're איסור, Issur, they're
all one big איסור Issur so to speak. They're all one big
איסור, Issur, one generic איסור. Issur. Now, according to אביי Abaye you
know why we had to say they were all sweet, because that's
what allowed the combination. According to רבא, Rava, the reason you have
to say they're all sweet is if they were just being eaten
outside of a mixture, you wouldn't have to say it, they combine
because they're all תועבה. Toeva. But if they all fall into a
mixture, in order for them to still not be בטל, Batel, they
have to make their presence felt, and that's why for רבא Rava
they also all need to be sweet. Okay, let's move on. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
חלא לגו חמרא. Chala Lego Chamra. What happens if vinegar falls into
wine? Is that מין במין Min Be-min or אינו מינו? Eino Mino?
So that's an easy question, they taste different and... They have different
names.
So דברי הכל divrei hakol נותן טעם, nosein taam, you go by
taste meaning because they're different types of things because they're called different
and different tastes. חמרא לגו חלא, chamra l'go chala, let's say you
have wine falling into vinegar. Now why don't you say the same
thing? Different names and different tastes? Because here's the story. It's the
what it means is you've got a huge vat of vinegar, of
kosher vinegar, and a drop of סתם יינם stam yeinam falls in.
So when the drop of סתם יינם stam yeinam is over this
huge barrel of vinegar, or I'm sorry, יין נסך yein nesech is
over this huge barrel of vinegar, the smell coming from the barrel
sort of changes the smell of the drop of wine before it
even hits the barrel. So when the drop of wine finally hits
the wine in the barrel, it already smells like vinegar. Alright, so
therefore the question is like this. So חמרא לגו חלא. chamra l'go
chala. אביי אמר במשהו, Abaye amar b'mashehu, you go by a משהו,
mashehu, it's considered מינו. mino. ורבא אמר בנותן טעם, v'Rava amar b'nosein
taam, you go by taste. אביי אמר במשהו, Abaye amar b'mashehu, you
go by a משהו. mashehu. Why?
ריחא חלא, reicha chala, at the moment the drop falls in it
already smells like vinegar. So something that smells like vinegar, the טעמא
חמרא tama chamra and it tastes like wine, חלא chala is considered
vinegar. והוי ליה מין במינו v'havei lei min b'mino and therefore it's
vinegar and vinegar, וכל מין במינו במשהו v'chol min b'mino b'mashehu and
therefore it goes by משהו. mashehu. רבא אמר בנותן טעם, Rava amar
b'nosein taam, you go by taste. ריחא חלא וטעמא חמרא חמרא, reicha
chala v'tama chamra chamra, if it smells like vinegar and it tastes
like wine, it's wine. והוי ליה מין בשאינו מינו v'havei lei min
b'she'eino mino and it's considered מין בשאינו מינו, min b'she'eino mino, וכל
מין בשאינו מינו בנותן טעם v'chol min b'she'eino mino b'nosein taam and
therefore since its identity here is wine, it's אינו מינו eino mino
and goes by נותן טעם. nosein taam. Now the funny thing is,
you want to understand like you want to map this onto the
earlier debate because when you say, when you ask the question, how
do you define something that smells like vinegar and tastes like wine?
You could say how would you categorize it, right? שם shem question,
which would be a question of name. What name would I give
it? Okay, or you could say what does it taste like? Now
taste, here's an interesting thing. What does it because I think more
taste comes from something's smell than it comes from its actual taste.
When somebody has a cold, because when you put something in your
mouth, the smell of it goes up your nasal passages and therefore
that's why when you have a cold things don't taste good because
or they barely taste because you're only getting the taste that comes
from your taste buds. So what you could actually say is, even
assuming we go by taste, right, if something smells something, even though
were you to be able to separate smell from taste and just
put it on your taste buds and have a cold you would
think you're drinking wine, but now that you don't have a cold
and you're drinking it, you think you're drinking vinegar because the taste,
the smell is overwhelming. So even from the measuring of what does
it taste like, the question is how big does the smell part
define halachically taste, right, which is a great question. So you could
have two questions. A, what do you call it, which is a
שם shem question, and B, what taste do you say it has
when it smells like vinegar and tastes like wine? So אביי Abaye
and רבא Rava are not clearly linking it to their earlier debate,
but were you to, let's see how that works. So אביי Abaye
says that
you go by smell. Now אביי Abaye is the one that says
interestingly you go by taste, right? אביי Abaye says that you categorize
things based on similar taste. So that would mean that אביי Abaye
would be saying smell defines taste. It actually works out like the
opposite than you would expect. I mean, you could understand a position
that smell defines taste and therefore since it smells like vinegar we're
going to put it in the tasting like vinegar category. But רבא'ס
Rava's I think particularly interesting because רבא Rava says you go by
name and here you got wine that's smelling like vinegar and still
tasting a little like wine and he's going to say I'm still
going to call it wine. Like I don't know, you know, I
don't know what people would say. I mean maybe that's what people
would say. They would say yeah, my wine's gone bad, my wine's
become vinegary, but they would still be referring to it as wine.
So it's interesting. So רבא Rava says vinegary wine, wine that smells
like vinegar, if we want to link this to their earlier debate,
if wine smells like vinegar people are still calling it wine, maybe
bad wine, but they're still calling it wine, and therefore it's מין
במינו. min b'mino. And אביי Abaye is saying if I'm going to
go by taste then its overwhelming taste now is a vinegary taste,
I'm going to call it vinegar. Anyway, so you could link it.
So the גמרא Gemara doesn't link it to the earlier debate, but
it's obviously almost asking to be linked to the earlier debate. But
the point I still want to make is this case of one
type of a taste and one type of a smell, you could
question both what type of a name do you give it, how
do people categorize it differently, and you could even question just purely
from the smell perspective, if we appreciate how much, I'm sorry, purely
from the taste perspective, if we appreciate how much smell defines taste,
determines taste in terms of the human experience, it's a really interesting
question that we might sort of still say, and that seems to
be אביי'ס Abaye's position. אביי Abaye goes by smell and he excuse
me, אביי Abaye goes by taste and he calls this wine with
a vinegary smell, he... calls it vinegar. So even from a perspective
of taste, he says smell determines taste. Yes, question? אפילו ריחא לא
מבטלינן. Afilu reicha lo mibatlinan. There you go. Okay. Yes. It's interesting.
About עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah you'd imagine to be part of קדשים
Kodashim but it's part of נזיקין. Nezikin. Right.
For this reason. Even נזיקין Nezikin seems, you know, like a miscategorization
or it doesn't belong. Right. Just an observation. Okay. Okay good. So
אביי Abaye so here we have this interesting question of a mixture
of taste and smell where אביי Abaye and רבא Rava disagree. אביי
Abaye goes by smell and רבא Rava goes by taste. And again
the irony is that אביי Abaye who generally emphasizes smell says here—I
keep misstating it, I repeated it just to say it right for
once and I blew it again. Anyway,
אביי Abaye goes by smell by the wine, even though his normal
position is that things are defined by taste, he says here that
the way I read אביי Abaye that smell determines taste. Or smell
is the more dominant determinant of taste and that if it smells
like vinegar we're going to call it vinegar. Okay so now the
גמרא Gemara continues.
Now, האי בסטיא, Hai bastia, another issue of smell but sort of
not when it's competing with taste, just smell by itself. So a
certain type of a בסטיא bastia which is like a pipette that
they would stick into a barrel of wine and smell to smell
the wine and to see if the wine was was good, okay,
or was it fermenting properly or whatever. So עובד כוכבים ודישראל, oved
kokhavim v'diYisrael if a non-Jew smells a Jew's wine, so שפיר דמי,
shapir dami, that's fine. He didn't touch it, he didn't move it,
we're okay.
ישראל ועובד כוכבים, Yisrael ve'oved kokhavim, if a Jew smells a non-Jew's
wine, תוספות Tosafot says you have to assume he's doing it for
free or else you got a problem about being paid for dealing
with יין נסך. yayin nesech. But anyway, if a Jew smells a
non-Jew's wine, so we've now separated out smell from the taste, okay?
Before we had smell and taste in you actually are eating it,
it's interwoven, and which one is determinant? Here you're just having the
smell experience, okay? You're smelling יין נסך. yayin nesech. אביי אמר אסור,
Abaye amar assur, it's forbidden. רבא אמר מותר, Rava amar mutar, it's
permissible. אביי אמר אסור, Abaye amar assur, ריחא מילתא היא. reicha milta
hi. So here he's consistent with the emphasis he gave on smell
before. So wine that had a vinegary smell he called vinegar. And
here he's saying if you just have the smell, you've done something
wrong by ingesting the smell of the wine,
okay? ריחא—ורבא אמר מותר, mutter permissible, ריחא לאו מילתא היא, reicha lav
milta hi, the smell is nothing. Now, what do we mean by
this question of is the smell something or not? So since we're
talking about יין נסך, yayin nesech, the most logical thing to say
is that the question is: is this considered to be הנאה, hana'ah,
benefit? Right when you smell something that's forbidden in הנאה. hana'ah. And
there's actually an interesting debate in תוספות Tosafot about whether when something
is forbidden in הנאה—but hana'ah it's not—if it's made for smelling, like
if you have roses that are forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah, you know,
then everybody agrees that it's אסור assur to smell, to get benefit
from it. But if something is not made for smelling and you
happen to get, you know, get a nice smell from it, is
that a violation of איסורי הנאה? issurei hana'ah? But that does not
seem to be the debate—so maybe that would be the debate of
אביי Abaye and רבא. Rava. You know, wine which is basically made
for drinking, it's not basically made for smelling. Is it a violation
of the איסור הנאה issur hana'ah of wine to smell it? Okay.
That doesn't explain the עובד כוכבים oved kokhavim ודישראל v'diYisrael, part, the
רישא. reisha. Well that's—no, that's completely a side point. Why can't he
smell my wine? Yeah, but why would they even bring it up?
That's a separate point. תוספות Tosafot just says it's to tell you
you're not גוזר gozer the flip case. Okay, but anyway, one way
to have explained this debate is it's specifically about יין yayin and
a question about is smell a real problem by איסורי הנאה. issurei
hana'ah. It's a גמרא Gemara in פסחים Pesachim about that also, about
ריחא, reicha you know, if קול ומראה וריח יש בהן משום מעילה
kol u'mareh v'reiach yesh bahen mishum me'ilah and so on. That would
be one way to explain it.
But it doesn't fit as the גמרא Gemara continues, because the גמרא
Gemara is now going to link their debate to a similar debate
by תרומה, terumah, and תרומה terumah is not forbidden in הנאה. hana'ah.
So let's see what the debate in תרומה terumah is and then
let's go back and see if we can try to understand more,
better what they're debating here, okay? So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רבא מנא אמינא לה דריחא לאו
כלום הוא. Amar Rava mana amina lah de'reicha lav klum hu. Where
do I get this idea that smell doesn't matter? Okay, they're very
nicely consistent again with what they said before about the wine with
the vinegary smell. אביי Abaye paid attention to the smell and called
it vinegar, and רבא Rava did not. Here you have smell by
itself. So רבא Rava says where do I get this sense that
smell doesn't matter? דתנן, De'tenan, we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, תנור
שהסיקו בכמון של תרומה. Tanur she'hisiko be'chamon shel terumah. You lit up
an oven with כמון, chamon, which is what's כמון? chamon? Cumin. Cumin
תרומה terumah cumin. So תרומה terumah is not אסור בהנאה, assur be'hana'ah,
so that's the key here. ואפה בו את הפת. Ve'afah bo et
ha'pat. And now you baked a bread in this oven. הפת מותרת,
Hapat muteret, even though this bread has a cuminey like flavor, aroma
to it, it's permissible. Right? And it's not considered תרומה. terumah. לפי
שאין טעם כמון אלא ריח כמון. Lefi she'ein ta'am chamon ela reiach
chamon. You only got the smell of the cumin, you didn't get
the taste of the cumin. The smell was in the air. ואביי—
Ve'Abaye So, look, so there is my proof that the smell doesn't
matter, it's not like the תרומה trumah is present. אביי, Abaye, אביי
Abaye will say back, no. שאני התם דמיקלי איסוריה. shani hatam d'mikleh
issurei. There,
you first burnt the cumin, you only had the aroma floating by
itself. So that, that sort of detached aroma is not considered to
be like the thing itself. But if you directly smell it, smell
the wine, smell the cumin, that it is a problem. Now,
what problem is it? תרומה trumah is not forbidden in הנאה. hana'ah.
So what תוספות Tosafot says, you almost have to say it, is
תוספות Tosafot says, the question here is, is it considered like you
ingested the thing itself? Okay?
If I were to be able to, I don't know, if I
have this forbidden piece of, you know, I'm not allowed, even if
something is only forbidden to be eaten, right? But what does it
mean to eat? Right? You know, if we, let's say I have
this טרפה traife piece of, this piece of תרומה, trumah, and I
lick it. Okay? So you could say, you know, so you could
say, oh, I only got the taste of it, I didn't actually
chew it and swallow it and ingest it. They say, no, טעם
כעיקר, ta'am k'ikar, you tasted it, that's like you ingested it. So
let's say I don't lick it, let's say I smell it. Okay?
If I smell it, is that somehow like I ingested some of
the תרומה trumah itself? Is it a type of אכילה? achilah? says
תוספות, Tosafot, that's the question. It's not a הנאה hana'ah question. For
whatever reason, we'll say there's no הנאה. hana'ah. תוספות Tosafot gives a
scenario where maybe it's so powerful and overwhelming it's not a pleasurable
experience. But nevertheless, some of that aroma went into your body. Now,
if you had the detached aroma, that's not actually תרומה, trumah, that's
not actually יין, yayin, that's just wine smell. I didn't drink or
eat wine. But if I'm directly have the wine in front of
me or the תרומה trumah in front of me and I'm smelling
it, and it's sort of like entering my body through that smell,
and the thing itself is there, the question is to some degree
is it like I ingested the thing? That's the question. So אביי
Abaye says if you're getting that smell, it's like you ingested it,
whereas רבא Rava says no. If you, if you put it in
your mouth, you ingested it. You know, now of course the funny
thing is you could smell it with your mouth, right? You could
go like this, go like that, you know, and then it goes
up your nasal passages. It is sort of similar to the previous
discussion of the combination of taste and smell. So אביי Abaye says,
look, this goes through your mouth and your nose and whatever and
it's like you ingested it, and רבא Rava says no, if it's
not actually eating the food itself, if it's just ingesting the, as
it were, the ריח, reiach, that's not like an act of eating
and it's not a problem. Okay, so this is their debate.
So let's continue. So it says like this. אמר רב מרי כתנאי,
Amar Rav Mari k'tannai,
this is actually linked to a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. הרודה פת
חמה ונתנה על פי חבית Harodeh pat chamah v'netanah al pi chavit
של יין, shel yayin,
somebody basically took some hot bread and put it right out of
the oven and put it on top of a barrel of wine,
יין של תרומה. yayin shel trumah. רבי מאיר אוסר, Rabbi Meir osser,
don't, you can't eat the bread because it's absorbed the smell of
the wine. ורבי יהודה מתיר, v'Rabbi Yehuda mattir, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
permits it. ורבי יוסי מתיר בשל חטים ואוסר בשל שעורים, v'Rabbi Yossi
mattir b'shel chittin v'osser b'shel se'orin, he splits between wheat bread and
barley bread. Barley is a problem מפני שהשעורים שואבות mipnei she-hasse'orin sho'avot
because the barley bread will more absorb the taste, the smell of
the wine. מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי, Mai lav b'ha kamiflagi, it seems
to be this is the debate. דמר סבר ריחא מילתא היא, D'mar
savar reiha milta hi, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who has a problem
and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi who has a problem based on the
circumstances feel that smell's a problem. ומר סבר ריחא ולאו כלום היא,
U'mar savar reiha v'lav klum hi, and the other one, רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says it's okay, says smell is not an issue. So
the גמרא Gemara says, לרבא ודאי תנאי היא. L'Rava vadai tannai hi.
So רבא, Rava, who says smell is not an issue, has to
concede that here you have תנאים Tannaim that hold that smell is
an issue. So he could say, I go like רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda who says there's no problem, but I admit that there are
other תנאים Tannaim who disagree with me, the other תנאים Tannaim who
say that smell is a problem. אביי מי לימא תנאי היא, Abaye
mi leima tannai hi, does אביי Abaye have to say it's a
debate of תנאים? Tannaim? אמר לך אביי לא לאו מי איתמר עלה,
Amalakh Abaye lo lav mi itmar lah, no, I don't have to
say it's a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. I could say everybody agrees
in principle it's a problem. The whole debate here is, when do
we say the smell in practice is actually absorbed? לאו מי איתמר
עלה אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר ריש לקיש, Lav mi itmar
lah amar Rabbah bar bar Chanah amar Reish Lakish, בפת חמה וחבית
פתוחה, b'pat chamah v'chavit ptuchah, if the bread is hot and the
barrel is open, דברי הכל אסור, divrei hakol assur, even רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda would say it's a problem because then he would say
that the smell's absorbed. בפת צוננת וחבית מגופה, B'pat tzonenet v'chavit megufah,
if the bread is cold and the barrel is sealed, דברי הכל
מותרת, divrei hakol muteret, everybody would say it's permissible, nothing is absorbed.
לא נחלקו, Lo necheliku, the debates of the תנאים Tannaim here, רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי יוסי, Rabbi
Yossi, is not in principle. In principle ריחא reicha, is a problem.
The debate is in terms of the specifics. Are, you know, is
the smell actually absorbed in this case or in that case? לא
נחלקו אלא בפת חמה וחבית מגופה, Lo necheliku ella b'pat chamah v'chavit
megufah, either a hot bread and a sealed barrel, או בפת צוננת
וחבית פתוחה o b'pat tzonenet v'chavit ptuchah and a cold bread and
an open barrel. So you have one thing that leads to absorption
and one that doesn't. And then the point is, רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda would say, I don't think it ever gets absorbed. רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says, I always think it gets absorbed and Yossi says
depends on wheat or barley. והא דידי, v'ha didi, in my case
נמי, nami, the case of smelling the barrel of wine, כפת חמה
וחבית פתוחה דמי, ke'pas chamah v'chavis pesuchah dami, is a straight case
of smell, there's no question you're getting the smell therefore it's an
issue. So Abaye says, look, I would say that everybody here agrees
smell's an issue, their only question is whether it gets absorbed or
not, but in a case where you definitely have the smell it's
definitely a problem. Okay, now, by the way I should say that
if we combine this case to the discussion before, right, this case
is a little bit a midpoint between the air of the aroma
left behind by the wine and there's no wine present where there
the Gemara says if it's not בעין be'en it's not an issue,
it's just like it's just this you know this detached aroma. Here,
when you go ahead and eat the bread, you're not directly engaging
with the wine. So you could just say this is just detached
aroma, it's not a problem. But somehow it's become real because it
got absorbed into something physical. It now is part of the bread,
right? So and the bread directly got it from the wine. So
the idea is the same way that Abaye says the same way
that if my face is over this barrel of wine and I
smell it, it's like I've ingested wine, when this bread is directly
over the barrel of wine and the smell comes up, it's like
the wine has gone into the bread. Okay, so Abaye says smell
is a vehicle or a way of conceptualizing it. By the way,
here's an interesting halachic point. You know what it means when you
smell something? I asked once a like a scientist like what does
that mean like if I have a piece of steak and I'm
smelling it, what's going into my nose? So they basically said yeah
tiny little particles of steak are going into your nose. It's not
like it's something other than that, right? So there's nothing different from
the steak that's called smell of steak. It's just you know it's
just aerosolized steak that's now, which they said is like pretty disgusting
if you think about like what happens when you smell a baby's
diaper or whatever, but okay anyway I thought thank you for that
bit of information. Now I've shared it with you. Anyway, so once
you realize that basically it is little pieces of wine, you know,
that have just transformed in state that are going into the bread,
Abaye says that's wine. So there's wine in the bread, okay, so
and therefore there's wine going into your nose and mouth and therefore
you've basically eaten wine. And therefore Abaye says smelling it is like
ingesting it and eating it or like it's now in the bread,
okay, especially when it's directly in contact with that original thing. So
the bread is directly over the barrel of wine. And Rava says
if the physical wine itself, what I relate to as wine, you
know, the physical wine itself doesn't get mixed in the bread or
doesn't go down your throat, it's not a problem. Okay, so this
is the debate of Abaye and Rava whether ריחא מילתא. reicha milsa.
Now I just want to say one sentence about this huge Tosafos
because there's a whole interesting issue about the whole question about can
we cook in an oven with treif meat or even I mean
even alternate kosher and treif or whatever. So the Gemara basically discusses
that in the context of ריחא מילתא היא reicha milsa hi whether
smell is a thing because there's assumed like you only have the
smell, you don't have the thing itself that's in the oven like
this case that we just heard a case of an oven and
the cumin and whatever. So Tosafos's got a question because here we
should assume we rule like Rava against Abaye. And Rava says okay
that ריחא reiha is מותר that ריחא reicha isn't a problem. But
in the סוגיא sugya in פסחים Pesachim where it talks about ריחא,
reicha it seems to come to the conclusion that ריחא reicha, is
a problem. So which one of these do you go by, you
know, in terms of this issue about the use of an oven?
And that leads Tosafos to a whole question about like are these
the same scenarios of ריחא reicha or not? So I want to
just look read one line at the end because it's very relevant
to the fact that it's almost Pesach. Okay, so if you look
at this big Tosafos about רבא אמר ריחא מילתא היא. Rava amar
reicha milsa hi. Okay, I mean I guess let me just read
you the first line so you see the sugya it's connected to.
So he says פרק כיצד צולין Perek Keitzad Tzolin פליגי נמי רב
ולוי pligi nami Rav v'Levi בריחא be'reicha גבי בשר שמן שצלאו עם
בשר נבילה. gabi basar shamen she'tzala'o im basar neveilah. You roasted fatty
meat with kosher meat with treif not kosher with treif thin meat.
רב אסר ולוי שרי. Rav assar v'Levi shari. Rav forbids it because
the taste goes the taste gets absorbed and Levi permits it. והתם
תניא כוותיה דרב v'hasam tanya kavasei d'Rav and there we rule like
Rav which should basically sound like the conclusion should be it's forbidden.
ופירוש שם רש"י u'peirush sham Rashi דאף על גב דתניא כוותיה דרב
דאסר הלכה כלוי דשרי. d'af al gav d'tanya kavasei d'Rav d'assar halacha
k'Levi d'shari. We rule like Levi that it's not a problem you
cooking things in the same oven. Why? משום דרבא סבר כוותיה הכא
גבי פת תתאה והלכה כרבא לגבי אביי. mishum d'Rava savar kavasei hacha
gabi pas tata'ah v'halacha k'Rava lgabi Abaye. ופסק כך רש"י פרק כיצד
צולין. u'pasak kach Rashi Perek Keitzad Tzolin.
So he says because we rule like Rava and Rava here says
ריחא לאו מילתא היא. reicha lav milsa hi. And then he goes
on and discusses it and says it's not so clear. Anyway let's
look at the end of Tosafos this is a whole question about
ovens and do we pasken ריחא מילתא reicha milsa or לאו מילתא.
lav milsa. Overwhelmingly the פסק psak is ריחא לאו מילתא reicha lav
milsa by ovens. Other questions come up about steam and so on.
Anyway if you look at the end of this Tosafos he says
the following. He says... ואל חיטה. v'al chita. ואחיתא וחמיץ ve-achita ve-chametz
if you look at the אמר רבא Amar Rava the next תוספות
אמר רבא Tosfos Amar Rava and you go up one, two, three,
four, five lines above that you see it says ואחיתא וחמיץ ve-achita
ve-chametz it says ואחיתא וחמיץ שנמצאת באחת מן המצות בי"ד. ve-achita ve-chametz
she-nimtzas be-achas min ha-matzos be-yud daled.
So they baked a little מצה matzah on the 14th and they
found a little piece of kernel of grain left over which they
were concerned was חמץ. chametz. לא מיבעיא קודם שש שעות דמותרות האחרות
lo mibaya kodem shesh sha'os demuteres acheros everything
and then how about the other matzahs that were baked together with
it? So they were all baked in the same oven but if
anything transferred it only transferred by smell, it didn't touch the other
matzahs. תוספות Tosfos says so before the sixth hour of the day
they are permissible לפי שביטל בשישים. lefi she-batel be-shishim. חמץ chametz is
only במשהו be-mashehu once it's actually פסח. Pesach. Okay כמו חמץ שלא
בזמנו אלא אפילו לאחר שש שעות kemo chametz shelo bizmano ela afilu
le-achar shesh sha'os even if it's after midday on ערב פסח Erev
Pesach מותרות האחרות muteres acheros משום דלא הוי חמץ בזמנו וחמץ שלא
בזמנו אינו במשהו עד זמן הממש היינו בז' ימי של פסח. mishum
delo havi chametz bizmano ve-chametz shelo bizmano eino be-mashehu ad zman ha-mamash
hainu be-zayin yemei shel Pesach. So חמץ chametz is only במשהו be-mashehu
once the night of פסח Pesach begins. Even ערב פסח Erev Pesach
when it's אסור assur to eat חמץ chametz we still say it's
ביטל בשישים. batel be-shishim. Okay so תוספות Tosfos says it's baked in
the same oven, so baked in the same oven we're going to
say we're going to say ריחא לאו מילתא היא reicha lav milsa
hi and it's not enough and it's not like it gives טעם
ta'am and since it's before פסח Pesach it's בטל batel we don't
say it's אסור במשהו. assur be-mashehu. Okay. What you're saying is if
you have a mixture with one and sixty ערב פסח Erev Pesach
you can use it on פסח? Pesach? Yes, technically speaking that is
correct. Don't try to get the הכשר hechsher to it, but yes.
Okay. Now if you go to the end of the line ואם
אפו המצות בשבעת ימי הפסח ve-im afu ha-matzos be-shiva yemei ha-Pesach one
minute ונמצא חיטה וחמץ באחת מהן. ve-nimtza chita ve-chametz be-achas mehen. However
תוספות Tosfos has תוספות's Tosfos combination is ריחא מילתא reicha milsa or
not מילתא. milsa. תוספות's Tosfos split is you know what, if something
transfers by smell it's not like it's there as if it's giving
taste, but certainly there are trace amounts. So it would be a
במשהו be-mashehu problem.
You follow me? So if things are cooked nearby and the smell
transfers we פסקן pasken like רבא Rava here or whatever that ריחא
לאו מילתא reicha lav milsa but לאו מילתא lav milsa means no
taste is present and it's not tastable or whatever, but certainly there's
enough there that transferred through the smell that there's a trace amount.
So it becomes a problem by things that are אסור במשהו. assur
be-mashehu. So this becomes the issue of a not כשר לפסח kasher
le-Pesach oven on פסח. Pesach. Right? If you you know so some
people will say you're going somewhere or whatever can you use an
oven that's used for טרייף treif things? I mean I know people
nowadays have two ovens for everything or they wait 24 hours but
there are plenty of שיטות shittos to rely on that if there's
no בעין be-en you know you can use an oven that was
used for טרייף treif you know for טרייף treif food or whatever.
Okay but and תוספות Tosfos did it all the time to cook
even at the same time with טרייף treif food. Anyway that was
earlier in the תוספות. Tosfos. But by פסח Pesach that's where we
start being worried because there even a במשהו be-mashehu matters and there
we might say that the issue of the residual smell right? Now
תוספות Tosfos by the way was only talking about when they were
baked at the same time. To think that there's still a smell
problem after it was cooked earlier and maybe there's some smell in
the walls that now comes out like that's a whole other level
of concern. But anyway תוספות Tosfos was assuming that during the year
earlier in תוספות Tosfos I didn't read it but you could read
he would have them cook טרייף treif and כשר kosher products in
the same oven at the same time and say ריחא לאו מילתא
היא reicha lav milsa hi and the smell doesn't transfer. But for
פסח Pesach cooked at the same time with חמץ chametz that's a
problem because that might be an issue of a במשהו. be-mashehu. So
that's the last line where he says he says אבל אם אפו
המצות בשבעת ימי הפסח ונמצא חיטה וחמץ באחת מהן כולן אסורות. aval
im afu ha-matzos be-shiva yemei ha-Pesach ve-nimtza chita ve-chametz be-achas mehen kulan
assuros. Okay. ובתנור נמי יש לאסור דאף על גב דשמנינן ריחא לאו
מילתא היא מכל מקום ניהי דטעם ליכא מכל מקום משהו בעלמא איכא
ואפילו במשא תנור u-be-tannur nami yesh le-assor de-af al gav de-shamneinan reicha
lav milsa hi mi-kol makom nehi de-tam leka mi-kol makom mashehu be-alma
ika ve-afilu be-massa tannur
and even though it's an oven what he means by an oven
is even though it's baking because we would normally assume taste transfers
more by cooking than by baking. Baking everything is dry. Alright so
anyway this issue of ריחא מילתא reicha milsa is not just a
question of smelling wine it's a question about using ovens. And the
basic issue is can you use ovens at the same time? תוספות
Tosfos would have taken it as obvious that you could use ovens
one after the other. That's like the גמרא Gemara about once the
cumin is burnt up it's not a problem. But can you even
use ovens at the same time?
And תוספות's Tosfos basic conclusion is for תוספות Tosfos I'm not saying
this הלכה למעשה halacha le-maaseh תוספות Tosfos basically said you could cook
טרייף treif and כשר kosher in the same oven at the same
time ריחא לאו מילתא היא reicha lav milsa hi okay but and
then he but he says for חמץ chametz certainly בדיעבד be-diavad it's
okay but he says חמץ chametz בפסח be-Pesach at least we have
to be concerned that ריחא reicha is a במשהו be-mashehu and that
would be a problem if it was cooked on פסח Pesach itself
because then it's אסור אפילו במשהו. assur afilu be-mashehu. Okay we'll end
with that.